Guide to the Adolph Ross Papers and Photographs ALBA.137
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Adolph Ross Papers and Photographs
1938-1998, (Bulk 1983-1996)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ross, Adolph.
ALBA.137
3.5 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Adolph Ross was a volunteer in the Spanish Civil War, serving with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. He returned to New York severely wounded and went on to serve in the U.S. Army Air Corps in World War II. In later life he devoted himself to compiling biographical information on U.S. volunteers in the Spanish Civil War. Several versions of his annotated list were privately published and distributed by the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in the 1980s and 1990s. The collection includes multiple annotated drafts of the list, Ross’s files on and correspondence with a number of individual veterans and their family and friends, and some documents and memorabilia belonging to Ross himself.
Provenance
The Adolph Ross Papers came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Adolph Ross was born in New York City. The son of a Polish-English mother and an Austrian-born father, Ross spent his infancy in a Knights of Pythias orphanage, later acquiring the surname Ross from his mother’s second husband.
Ross became involved in politics at a young age, joining the Young Communist League and the National Student League while still in high school. In 1937 Ross volunteered for service in the Spanish Civil War, but was not granted permission until 1938, when he obtained a Spanish visa and traveled under the pseudonym Adolfo Rodriguez. In Spain he fought in the Ebro Campaign and in August 1938 was severely wounded while fighting in the Sierra Pandols. He returned to New York on December 31, 1938.
After service in the U.S. Army Air Corps as a Link Trainer instructor, Ross moved to Long Island with his wife Lillian and in the late seventies began compiling lists for a complete biographical directory of those who served in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Originally sponsored by the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB), the project continued under the auspices of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA). ALBA has planned to expand and publish the project data. Although Ross printed several versions of the “ALBA Biographical Dictionary Project” in the 1980s and 90s, he intended that the data included would be further refined. After his death in 1998, ALBA Executive Board member and Spanish Civil War historian Christopher Brooks continued Ross’s research, amassing additional biographical data on Lincoln Brigade veterans and other Americans who served in Spain.
Adolph Ross’s project was the basis of a list of Lincoln Brigade volunteers and medical personnel included in a souvenir brochure (No Pasaran! The 50th Anniversary of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade) published by ALBA/VALB in 1986. This list, with additions and corrections by Tamiment Library staff and others, is available on the web site of the Tamiment Library, at: http://www.nyu.edu/library/bobst/research/tam/alba_names.html
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Biographical Dictionary Project, 1951-1993, consists of draft copies of the Biographical Dictionary Project listing, as well as correspondence, reports, notes and veterans lists from a number of international archives.
Series II: Individual Files, 1943-1998, consists of correspondence with veterans, their families, historians, and others involved in Spanish Civil War history. Much of this correspondence includes biographical information about specific veterans, some of it prepared in response to Ross’s inquiries. Personal correspondence between Ross and friends/colleagues is also included. The series also contains a file of personal and biographical material relating to Ross himself.
Series III: General Files, 1938-1998, consists of clippings, pamphlets and general mailings. Also included are VALB-related documents and a folder of letters and clippings documenting Ross’s trip to Spain in 1973.
Series IV: Photographs, 1973, consists of six color snapshots (3 of Adolph Ross and 2 scenic views) taken on a visit to Valencia, the Alhambra, and Teruel in 1973.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Missing Title
I, Biographical Dictionary Project, 1951-1993.
II, Individual Files, 1943-1998.
III. General Files, 1938-1998.
IV, Photographs, 1973.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Drafts (documents); Research (document genres).; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Personal papers.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Biography.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Biography files.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Ross, Adolph.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV--Biography; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV
- Series I: Biographical Dictionary Project, 1951-1993.
  - Amendments and Corrections, Aug 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Amendments and Corrections, Aug 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Draft (bound): Annotated in the 1980s, undated (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Draft (annotated), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Draft (Book #1), Dec 1, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Draft (Book #30), Dec 1, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Draft (with August 1990 Addendum), Dec 1, 1985, Aug 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Introductory Material (Draft), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter to Veterans, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mailing Record, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript (draft, rough), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript (draft), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript (draft), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript (finished version), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript (misc. pages), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notes, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notes, Lists, and Addenda, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Report to Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) Board, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Veteran Lists (I), 1983-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Veteran Lists (II), 1983-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Veteran Lists: Addresses, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Veteran Lists: Cameron Stewart, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Veteran Lists: Deserters, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Veteran Lists: Missing, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Veteran Lists: Mortalities, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Veteran Lists: Moscow International Brigade Archives, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Veteran Lists: Sailing Lists, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Veteran Lists: Senate Subcommittee on Soviet Activity in the United States (excerpt, “Passport List”), 1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Veteran Lists: Working Copy (heavily annotated), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series II: Individual Files, 1943-1998.
  - Acker, Sylvia, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Alexander, William, 1994, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Allen, Richard S., 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Amatniek, Ernie, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Amery, Al, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Antin, Charles (re: Raleigh Frohman), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Arnold, Gary (re: David White), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Attarian, Aram, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Azar, Joseph (re: Vernald Bube), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Bailey, Bill, 1984-1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Balchowsky, Ed, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Barnett, Jim, 1973, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Bender, Ed, 1984-1985, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Berch, Victor, 1977, 1984-1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Berkowitz, Norman, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Berman, Jennie, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Boyer, Diane (re: Toiva Maki), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Brandt, Joe and Sylvia, 1985, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Bridenthal, Ken, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Brooker, Chris, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Brown, Archie, 1984, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Burke, Lee, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Burke, Paul, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Burns, Paul, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Cagan, Steve (re: David Shappiro), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Carroll, Peter, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Chase, Allen (re: Ralph Wardlaw), 1992 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Cesarini, Jaun Carlos, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Chesler, Frank, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Clay-Micola, Pedro, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Cogswell, Ted (aka Ted Lewis), 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Cohen, Milton, 1985-1993 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Colow, Maury, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Copeland, Abe, 1981, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Corbin, Rudy (re: James Gunning), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Cueria, Basilio, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Cullinen, George, 1983-1996 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Delaney, Charles (re: Andy Delaney), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Donegian, Maxim (re: Bedros Donegian), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Eberwein, Robert (Tamiment Library), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Eider, Kate, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Entwistle, Tom, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Eriksson, Per (re: John Malmquist), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Fasanella, Ralph, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Feinsilber, Pam (re: Alvah Bessie), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Felsen, Milt, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Fern, Gene and Flora, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Fisher, Harry, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Fisher, Irving (re: James Yates), 1993 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Fishman, Moe, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Forester, Clarence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Frankel, I., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Frazee, Tom (re: Harry Haywood), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Friedman-Eldridge, Muriel (re: Maurice W. Freidman), undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Geiser, Carl, 1984-1997 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Gianfortoni, Elenore (re: Joseph Gianfortoni), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Girling, Frank, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Glenn, Joseph, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Goldring, Benjamin (re: Vernon Romayne Selby and other volunteers), 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Goldstein, Debi (re: Ben Goldstein), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Gordon, Lou, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Graeber, Ken, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Gramat, Morris (aka Morris Teitelbaum), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Grundblatt, J., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Hanzel, John Bill, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Harriman, Manny, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Healy, Dorothy (re: Rincon), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Heisler, Gus, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Heitman, Edward, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hendrikson, Roz, 1984, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hopper, Dale, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Juusela, Jyrvki (on Finnish and Finnish-American volunteers), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Iaffa, Fernando, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Iceland, Ben, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Inglis, Amirah, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Jural, Diane Marshall (re: Joseph Sacalauskas), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Kailin, Clarence, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Kanes, Lelage G. (re: Harry Levine et al.), undated (Box 3, Folder 13a)
  - Kasinof, Lee (re: Ben Kasinof), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Kaufman, Charles, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Kaufman, Sid, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Keenan, Thomas, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Kier, Duncan, 1984-1985, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Kormes, Karl, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Koslow, Al, 1985, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Kossean, Armand, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Kramer, Jacob, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Lamb, Leonard, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Lammert, Anita C. (“Having Our Say” Project, Seattle), 1996 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Landis, Art, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Lending, Ed, 1984-1995 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Levenson, Leonard, 1984-1993 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Lipton, Eunice, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Lister, Frank, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Lopez, Jules H., 1993 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Lubelski, Benjamin, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Ludwick, Percy, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - MacLeod, Don, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Maio, Maureen, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Maki, Martin, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Malbin, Virginia, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Marantz, Ray, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Martin, Fredericka, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Mates, Lydia (re: Dave Metropolitan), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Mattson, Matti, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - McIntire, Peg (re: Joseph Dallet), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Medrano, Juan (re: Joe Carson aka Jacob Karson), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Merges, Elmer S., 1984 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Michaut, R., 1981 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Minor, Ben, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Momryk, Myron (on Canadian volunteers), 1993, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Mouton, Roy, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Murra, John, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Myles, Naomi (re: James Joseph Byrne/Byron), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Nelson, Steve, 1982-1993 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Nicolletto, Italo, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Nusser, Charles, 1984, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - O’Brien, J. Kevin (Freedom of Information and Privacy Act request), 1998 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - O’Flaherty, Steven (re: Thomas O’Flaherty), 1987 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Osheroff, Abe, 1986-1993 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Osipenko, Lt. General Alexander, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Pappas, Nick (re: Mary Pappas), 1993 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Patai, Frances, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Patzert, Rudolf, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Perlman, Norman, 1984, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Persoff, Jim, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Petkov, Goldie, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Postek, Stanley, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Prago, Albert and Ruth, 1986-1993 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Ragner, Albin, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Rauschwald, Mark, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Reed, Robert, 1984-1994 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Robinson, John, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Rosenstein, Herman, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Rosenthal, Lee, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Ross, Adolph: Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1943-1998 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Rossen, John, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Rowlson, Lester, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Rudner, Sidney (re: James Besante), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Salzman, Salman J., 1983-1994 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Schneider, Theodore, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Schuetrum, Walter J., 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Seidman, Laurie, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Sennet, William, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Shapiro, Saul, 1984, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Shifrin, Roy, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Smith, David, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Smith, Randall (“Pete”), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Smorodin, Abe, 1982-1994 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Sosa, Carmen, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Sperber, Gus, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Spiller, Sam (re: Chil Crane), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Stamm, Morris, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Steck, Robert, 1984-1996 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Sussman, William, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Tabb, Herbert (Hy), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Tanz, Al, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Tisa, John, 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Toney, Anthony, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Torrance, Mary, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Totis, Zoia-Luigi, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Vass, Joseph (Vienna Council of Labor, Social Science Library), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Vogel, Joseph, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Wachtel, Marion Merriman, 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Wallach, Jesse, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Walters, Sam, 1991-1997 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Warren, Alvin, 1986, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Watson, Robert, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Weiner, Milton, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Weinerman, Al, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Weissman, Irving, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Wellman, Saul, 1985-1994 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Wheeler, Bill, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Wildegans, Gustave, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Wolff, Milton, 1984-1995 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Young, Joseph, 1984, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 111)
- Series III: General Files, 1938-1998.
  - Clippings, 1938, 1983-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - International Events, Flyers, etc., 1966, 1986-1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Mailings: Miscellaneous, 1998, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - New Mexican Veterans: Exhibit Panels (photocopies), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - “Sim”: Portfolio Pages, Signed by Veterans; VALB 25th Anniversary; Poster, Signed by Steve Nelson (photocopies), 1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - “Sing Out!” Thirtieth Anniversary Issue (signed by Pete Seeger), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Dimitroff Museum, Leipzig: Pamphlet, Dimitrov versus Goering, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Trip to Spain, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - VALB: Events, 1983-1998 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - VALB: Meetings, 1984, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Photographs, 1973.
  - Color snapshots (4 of Adolph Ross, 2 scenic views) taken on a visit to Valencia, the Alhambra, and Teruel in Spain, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)